<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Notes</title>
 <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//"/>
 <updated>2021-05-15T17:17:38-07:00</updated>
 <id>https://ludavid15.github.io/</id>
 <author>
   <name>David Lu</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//fluidFundamentals/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//fluidFundamentals</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To be clear, when we talk about fluid mechanics, we aren’t just talking about the second state of matter (liquid \(\subset\) fluid). It honestly would make a lot more sense if we called it “flow mechanics”, but too many textbooks have been printed now to change that. In any case, we’re stuck with the term fluid mechanics, so that’s what we’ll be working with here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we’ll be dealing with so called &lt;strong&gt;Newtonion fluids&lt;/strong&gt;. Non-newtonian fluids are weird, and I haven’t studied them, so there won’t be anything about them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, while we’re laying down the groundwork here, it’s important to mention that classic fluid mechanics is treated as a subset of continuum mechanics. This is known as an engineering model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Continuums are characterized by the existence of shear, and by being continuous (duh).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But watch out! When the density is really low, (such as in space) the continuum assumption falls apart, at which point we must switch over to modelcular dynamics. This is an important rule to remember generally speaking. Each equation we develop comes with it’s own set of assumptions that must be true or else our equation isn’t valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;newtonian-fluid&quot;&gt;Newtonian Fluid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Newtonian fluid has a linear relationship between stress and strain rate. Non-newtonian fluids have non-linear relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fundamentals&quot;&gt;Fundamentals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, we want to find the following properties as a function of location and time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pressure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Temperature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Density&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Velocity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceleration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the above information, we can find things like lift, drag, work, &amp;amp; heat transfer (all very important for engineering applications). In a complete model, all 5 of these properties are closely related. Not surprisingly, it’s also difficult to solve for all 5 properties at once. Thus, the subject of fluid mechanics is further broken up into categories based on assumptions and simplifications. These assumptions allow us to make certain variables independent of other variables. The three most important “categories” are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incompressible vs Compressible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inviscid vs Viscid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Laminar vs Turbulent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any combinations of the above labels are technically possible. Here are a few examples, and the respective sub-domains you get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compressible, Inviscid, Laminar = Shocks, expansion waves, acoustic waves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compressible, Viscid, Turbulent = Turbulent boundary layers, supersonic wakes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compressible, Viscid, Laminar = Hypersonic boundary layers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incompressible, Inviscid, Laminar = Potential flow theory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incompressible, Viscid, Laminar = Creeping flow, boundary layer theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve problems in fluid mechanics, we can borrow laws and theories that traditionally fall under other disciplines. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thermodynamics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conservation Equations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas Laws&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continuum Mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, we can make assumptions which are imposed as additional contraints. Common assumptions come from thermodynamics: isentropic, isobaric, isochoric, isothermal, steady, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;viscosity&quot;&gt;Viscosity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viscosity of a fluid $\mu$ defines the relationship between stress and strain. In most cases, we assume that the fluid is a Newtonian Fluid, meaning its stress and strain are related linearly. Here it is in two dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\tau=\mu\left(\frac{\partial u}{\partial y}+\frac{\partial v}{\partial x}\right)\]

\[Friction\ Force=\mu\nabla^2\vec{V}=\nabla\tau\]

&lt;p&gt;We can also define the second coefficient of viscosity as λ.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\xi=\lambda+\frac{2}{3}\mu\]
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Continuum Mechanics</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//continuumMechanics/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//continuumMechanics</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the common assumptions we make when working with fluids is that it forms a continuum. The individual atoms of a fluid are assumed to be tightly packed enough that we can approximate the collective molecular interactions. What are these collective molecular interactions? Well, pretty standard stuff actually. We assume that applying a force causes an object to move, or a body to deform. (Technically speaking, that stress is related to strain). And honestly well, that’s kinda it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason this assumption is so powerful is because it makes our model &lt;strong&gt;continuous&lt;/strong&gt;. This may seem pretty obvious at a glance, but working with stuff that is continuous is very different from working with stuff that is discrete! The reason as you may already have guessed: derivatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, so what can we do with continuums? Well, how about mass, momentum, and energy conservation? Sure enough. There are two ways to do this: with either a &lt;strong&gt;control mass&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;control volume&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conservation-of-mass&quot;&gt;Conservation of Mass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also known as continuity. Time rate of change of mass in the control volume (CV) is equal to the mass flux through the boundary. Or, in differential form, partial derivative of density plus mass flux is zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integral&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\frac{\partial}{\partial t}\iiint\rho dV=-\oiint{\rho\mathbit{u}\bullet\hat{\mathbit{n}}dA}\]

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conservative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\frac{\partial\rho}{\partial t}+\nabla\bullet\left(\rho\mathbit{u}\right)=0\]

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-conservative
\(\frac{D\rho}{Dt}+\nabla\bullet\left(\rho\mathbit{u}\right)=0\)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For (quasi) 1-dimensional steady flow, the mass flow rate can be expressed as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\dot{m}=\rho AV\]

&lt;p&gt;For 2D incompressible flow, we need to account for the velocity in two directions. In this case continuity can be expressed as:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{\partial u}{\partial x}+\frac{\partial v}{\partial y}=0\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conservation-of-momentum&quot;&gt;Conservation of Momentum&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time rate of change of momentum in the CV is equal to the advection term plus forces. Or in differential form, partial of momentum with respect to time plus advection term is equal to forces acting on the fluid element. Note that the right side of the equation is the substantial derivative. You may recognize these as the Navier-Stokes equations. Or another way of thinking about it, the Navier-Stokes equations are just a statement momentum conservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integral&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\frac{\partial}{\partial t}\iiint\rho udV=-\oiint\mathbit{u}\left(\rho\mathbit{u}\bullet\hat{\mathbit{n}}\right)dA-\oiint\left(P\hat{\mathbit{n}}\right)dA\]

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conservative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\frac{\partial\rho\mathbit{u}}{\partial t}+\left(\nabla\bullet\rho\mathbit{u}\right)\mathbit{u}=-\nabla P+\rho g+\nabla\tau+\mathbit{F}_{\mathbit{body}}\]

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-conservative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\rho\frac{D\mathbit{u}}{Dt}=-\nabla P+\rho g+\nabla\tau+\mathbit{F}_{\mathbit{body}}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conservation-of-energy&quot;&gt;Conservation of Energy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time rate of change is equal to advection term plus heat (both volumetrically and through the surface). Note that work done is encapsulated in the P/rho term in the advection integral. Or, the substantial derivative of total enthalpy is equal to time rate of change of pressure (work) and flux of heat. This is also a statement of the 1st law of thermodynamics. (Conservation of Energy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integral&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\frac{\partial}{\partial t}\iiint{\rho(e+\frac{1}{2}U^2)dV}=-\oiint{\rho\left(e+\frac{P}{\rho}+\frac{1}{2}U^2\right)\mathbit{u}\bullet\hat{\mathbit{n}}dA}+\iiint{\rho\dot{q}dV}-\oiint{\dot{q}^n\bullet\hat{\mathbit{n}}dA}\]

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conservative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\frac{\partial\rho e}{\partial t}+\nabla\bullet\left(\mathbit{u}(\rho e+P)\right)=0\]

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-Conservative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\rho\frac{Dh_o}{Dt}=\frac{\partial P}{\partial t}+\rho\dot{q}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conservative-vs-non-conservative-form&quot;&gt;Conservative vs Non-conservative Form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conservative equations are valid over discontinuities in the fluid flow. These mathematical models directly stems from applying conservation of mathematical quantities within a control volume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is this related to the idea of a conservative vector field? I’m actually unsure, but I like the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider the case where we take a derivative of a multivariable function. Mathematically, we can expand this derivative with the chain rule, but in doing so, we introduce terms that no longer describe a physical quantity. This is known as the non-conservative form. Most importantly, the non-conservative forms are not valid over discontinuities (i.e. shocks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;euler-equations&quot;&gt;Euler Equations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Euler equations represent conservation of momentum when viscous forces are neglected. This is also associated with the limit as Reynold’s number approaches infinity, and the regime of potential flow theory. In this regime, the no slip boundary condition cannot be applied, instead fluid flow at the wall is always tangential to the wall. The following equations have assumed incompressible flow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cartesian-coordinates&quot;&gt;Cartesian Coordinates&lt;/h4&gt;

\[x:\ \ \ \ \rho\left[\frac{\partial u}{\partial t}+u\frac{\partial u}{\partial x}+v\frac{\partial u}{\partial y}+w\frac{\partial u}{\partial z}\right]=-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}+\rho g_x\]

\[y:\ \ \ \ \rho\left[\frac{\partial v}{\partial t}+u\frac{\partial v}{\partial x}+v\frac{\partial v}{\partial y}+w\frac{\partial v}{\partial z}\right]=-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}+\rho g_y\]

\[z:\ \ \ \ \rho\left[\frac{\partial w}{\partial t}+u\frac{\partial w}{\partial x}+v\frac{\partial w}{\partial y}+w\frac{\partial w}{\partial z}\right]=-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}+\rho g_z\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;navier-stokes&quot;&gt;Navier-Stokes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Navier-Stokes is a general statement of conservation of momentum. The form presented here includes forces due to pressure, gravity, and viscous forces, but neglects other types of forces. This form has also assumed constant density and viscosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cartesian-coordinates-1&quot;&gt;Cartesian Coordinates&lt;/h4&gt;

\[x:\ \ \ \ \rho\left[\frac{\partial u}{\partial t}+u\frac{\partial u}{\partial x}+v\frac{\partial u}{\partial y}+w\frac{\partial u}{\partial z}\right]=-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}+\rho g_x+\mu\left[\frac{\partial^2u}{\partial x^2}+\frac{\partial^2u}{\partial y^2}+\frac{\partial^2u}{\partial z^2}\right]\]

\[y:\ \ \ \ \rho\left[\frac{\partial v}{\partial t}+u\frac{\partial v}{\partial x}+v\frac{\partial v}{\partial y}+w\frac{\partial v}{\partial z}\right]=-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}+\rho g_y+\mu\left[\frac{\partial^2v}{\partial x^2}+\frac{\partial^2v}{\partial y^2}+\frac{\partial^2v}{\partial z^2}\right]\]

\[z:\ \ \ \ \rho\left[\frac{\partial w}{\partial t}+u\frac{\partial w}{\partial x}+v\frac{\partial w}{\partial y}+w\frac{\partial w}{\partial z}\right]=-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}+\rho g_z+\mu\left[\frac{\partial^2w}{\partial x^2}+\frac{\partial^2w}{\partial y^2}+\frac{\partial^2w}{\partial z^2}\right]\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reynolds-transport-theorem&quot;&gt;Reynold’s Transport Theorem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;States that the total time rate of change of an extensive property (B) for a system, depends on the rate of change of the intensive property in the control volume and the flux of that property through the control volume. (Extensive = mass dependent and Intensive = mass independent). In other works, it relates the control mass view of a fluid to the control volume view of a fluid.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{DB_{sys}}{Dt}=\int_{cv}^{cv}\frac{\partial}{\partial t}(\rho b)dV+\int_{cs}^{cs}\rho b\left(\vec{v}\bullet\hat{n}\right)ds\]
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Viscous Flow</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//viscousFlow/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//viscous</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Unlike solids, fluids deform constantly under stress (in other words, a fluid &lt;strong&gt;flows&lt;/strong&gt;). How it flows is very much dependent on it’s &lt;strong&gt;viscosity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
Viscosity is to fluids what the modulus of elasticity is to solids. It relates the stress (amount of force) to strain (amount of deformation). Qualitatively, viscosity is a measure of a fluid&apos;s resistence to flowing. Things like honey have a very high viscosity, while air and water have comparatively lower viscosity. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viscous flow then, is the study of how a fluid’s viscosity affects its behavior. Viscous flow covers topics like boundary layers, low-speed flows, and small-scale flows. Coincidentally, the regimes in which viscous forces dominate is often incompressible, but this is not a hard and fast rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;viscosity&quot;&gt;Viscosity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viscosity of a fluid $\mu$ defines the relationship between stress and strain. In most cases, we assume that the fluid is a Newtonian Fluid, meaning its stress and strain are related linearly. Here it is in two dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\tau=\mu\left(\frac{\partial u}{\partial y}+\frac{\partial v}{\partial x}\right)\]

\[Friction\ Force=\mu\nabla^2\vec{V}=\nabla\tau\]

&lt;p&gt;We can also define the second coefficient of viscosity as λ.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\xi=\lambda+\frac{2}{3}\mu\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reynolds-number&quot;&gt;Reynold’s Number&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ratio between viscous forces and inertial forces. The lower the Reynold’s number, the more dominant viscous effects become. The Reynold’s number can also show when a flow transitions from laminar to turbulent flow. Where µ is the dynamic viscosity.&lt;/p&gt;

\[Re=\ \frac{\rho U_\infty L}{\mu}\]

&lt;p&gt;At very low Re, we get the Stokes equations. At very high Re, we get the Euler equations (potential flow theory).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;low-reynolds-number-flow-stokes-flow&quot;&gt;Low Reynold’s Number Flow (Stokes’ Flow)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the exact opposite regime of potential flow theory, in which viscous forces dominate over inertia forces. This is usually associated with low velocity, small scale, or highly viscous flows. Some applications can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fully developed duct flow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flow about immersed bodies (i.e. small particle dynamics)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lubrication theory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flow through porous media (mostly used for civil engineering)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the above assumption (i.e. very low Re), the momentum equation reduces to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\nabla P\approx\mu\nabla^2V\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;low-reynolds-number-flow-over-a-sphere&quot;&gt;Low Reynold’s Number Flow Over a Sphere&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By solving stokes equations with the boundary conditions for viscous flow past a sphere, the following stream function can be calculated:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\psi=\frac{1}{4}Ua^2{sin}^2(\theta)\left[\frac{a}{r}-\frac{3r}{a}+\frac{2r^2}{a^2}\right]\]

&lt;p&gt;This can be compared to the stream function found by applying potential flow theory about a sphere:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\psi=\frac{1}{2}Ur^2{sin}^2(\theta)\left[1-\frac{a^3}{r^3}\right]\]

&lt;p&gt;Solving the first equation for shear and pressure drag, we find an expression for the total drag on a sphere in the low Reynold’s number limit:&lt;/p&gt;

\[F=4\pi\mu Ua+2\pi\mu Ua\]

&lt;p&gt;Where the first term is the viscous contribution to drag, and the second term is the pressure contribution to drag. This is normalized by the area and dynamic pressure to find the drag coefficient.&lt;/p&gt;

\[C_d=\frac{2F}{\rho U^2\pi a^2}=\frac{24}{Re}\]

&lt;p&gt;This equation underpredicts drag for Reynold’s numbers larger than 1, since separation and wakes introduce greater pressure drag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;steady-flow-between-infinite-plates&quot;&gt;Steady Flow between Infinite Plates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another class of problem in which viscous forces dominate. We take the bottom plate to be stationary and assume some steady velocity for the top plate. There can also be a pressure gradient in the direction parallel to the plates. Due to viscosity, the motion of the top plate drags the top layer of fluid along with it. Eventually, some sort of velocity profile develops along this direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the limit that the top plate’s velocity tends to zero we get a Hagen-Poiseuille flow problem (the only that can drive the fluid forward is a pressure gradient). In the limit that the pressure gradient tends to zero we get a Couette flow problem (velocity of the top plate drives flow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general solution of the velocity profile is expressed below. The first equation is the general solution, while the second equation takes the lower wall to be stationary. Where τo is the shear stress at the wall where y=0, and uo is the velocity at the wall where y=0.&lt;/p&gt;

\[u\left(y\right)=\ -\frac{1}{2\mu}\left(-\frac{dP}{dx}\right)y^2+\frac{\tau_o}{\mu}y+u_o\]

\[u\left(y\right)=\ +\frac{1}{2\mu}\left(-\frac{dP}{dx}\right)y(h-y)+U\frac{y}{h}\]

&lt;p&gt;We can also solve for the volume flow rate per unit span by integrating over y.&lt;/p&gt;

\[Q=U\frac{h}{2}+\frac{h^3}{12\mu}\left(-\frac{dP}{dx}\right)\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unsteady-flow--infinite-plates&quot;&gt;Unsteady Flow &amp;amp; Infinite Plates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two problems within this category, known as Stokes 1st problem (an impulsively started plate) and Stokes’s 2nd problem (an oscillating plate). Unlike the previous problem, which solves for some steady state condition, these problems deal with transient situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1st-problem&quot;&gt;1st Problem:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stoke’s first problem covers the scenario of an impulsively started plate.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{u(y,t)}{U}=1-\erf{\left(\frac{\eta}{2}\right)}\]

\[\erf{\left(x\right)}=\ \frac{2}{\sqrt\pi}\int_{0}^{x}{e^{-x^2}dx\]

\[\eta=\ \frac{y}{\sqrt{\nu t}}}\]

&lt;p&gt;As time increases, the penetration height will increase. At infinite time, the entire fluid moves with velocity U. The above solution represents a non-dimensionalized solution, where η represents the ratio of position to penetration height scaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2nd-problem&quot;&gt;2nd Problem:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motion of the bottom plate is defined as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

\[U\left(t\right)=\ U_o\cos\funcapply(\omega t)\]

&lt;p&gt;The velocity profile above the plate and the stress at the wall can be solved to show the following:&lt;/p&gt;

\[u\left(y,t\right)=U_oe^{-y\sqrt{\sfrac{\omega}{2v}}}cos\left(\omega t-y\sqrt{\sfrac{\omega}{2v}}\right)\]

\[\tau_{wall}=\mu\frac{\partial u}{\partial y}=U_o\sqrt{\rho\mu\omega}sin\left(\omega t-\sfrac{\pi}{4}\right)\]

&lt;p&gt;The amplitude of the velocity oscillation decreases with distance from the plate. The ratio of viscosity to frequency determines the penetration height. Note that this ratio also affects a phase lead/lag, which changes with height, represented within the cosine term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pipes&quot;&gt;Pipes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although infinite plates are useful for understanding some of the concepts, they are exactly reflective of real life. What we do see plenty of though, is flow through pipes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hagen-poiseuille-circular-pipe-flow-model&quot;&gt;Hagen-Poiseuille Circular Pipe Flow Model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pressure driven viscous pipe flow. Given L is the length of pipe, Q is the volume flow rate, and some known diameter, we can find the pressure drop. Assumes laminar flow.&lt;/p&gt;

\[∆P= 8μLQπR4\]

\[u\left(r\right)=\ -\frac{1}{4\mu}\left(-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}\right)\left(r_o^2-r^2\right)\]

\[Q=\ \frac{\pi R^4}{8\mu}\left(\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}\right)\]

\[C_f=-\frac{\tau_w}{\sfrac{(1}{2})\rho{U_{ave}}^2}=\frac{16}{Re_D}\]

&lt;p&gt;Note that this may not be valid for short pipes, flow near the entrance, and fluids with low viscosity, or flow in a wide pipe. If flow is turbulent, you should switch over to the Darcy-Weisbach approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-realistic-pipe-flow-analysis&quot;&gt;More Realistic Pipe Flow Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For flow (both laminar and turbulent) in a pipe of constant diameter D, we can express the pressure across a given length as:
\(∆PL=fd(12)ρU2D\)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where fd is the Darcy friction factor. In the laminar regime, the Darcy Friction factor is equal to \(\sfrac{f_D=64}{Re}\). For turbulent regime values, the friction factor is dependent on the surface roughness. Look up results in a Moody Diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be inserted, Moody Diagram&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More commonly, pressure loss per unit length is replaced with head loss per unit length, S, where head loss is calculated as:
\(∆h= ρg∆P\)&lt;/p&gt;

\[S=∆hL=fd12gV2D\]

&lt;p&gt;Note that the friction factor in the turbulent regime can be calculated with turbulent flow theory and is not simply an empiric fit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;colebrook-interpolation-formula-turbulent--transition-regime&quot;&gt;Colebrook Interpolation Formula (Turbulent &amp;amp; Transition Regime)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provides an easy way to find the friction factor for a given surface roughness and Reynold’s number. \(\Lambda\) here is the friction factor.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{1}{\Lambda^{1/2}}\approx-2.0\log_{10}{\left(\frac{k/D}{3.7}+\frac{2.51}{Re_D\sqrt\Lambda}\right)}-0.8\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hydraulic-diameter&quot;&gt;Hydraulic Diameter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For non-circular pipes, an equivalent diameter can be found, known as the hydraulic diameter. This allows you to analyze the pipe as if it were circular.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\rho\left(\frac{\partial u_e}{\partial t}+u\frac{\partial u_e}{\partial x}\right)=-\frac{\partial P}{\partial x}\]

&lt;h2 id=&quot;boundary-layers&quot;&gt;Boundary Layers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boundary layers are an incredibly important phenomena arising due to viscous forces. As before, we require that the velocity of the fluid at the wall is equal to the velocity of the wall. Only through BL analysis can we determine things like the lift, drag, and heat flux of objects moving through a fluid (such as a wing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, we’ll focus on laminar boundary layers, however, it is possible for something known as &lt;strong&gt;Boundary Layer Separation&lt;/strong&gt; to occur. When this happens, the fluid ceases to flow past objects in a nice smooth fashion, and trips into turbulent flow. This leads to the topic of &lt;strong&gt;Tubulent Boundary Layer&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a whole other beast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2d-boundary-layer-similarity-solutions&quot;&gt;2D Boundary Layer Similarity Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, it is easier to create the following similarity variables, defined using the velocity potential:&lt;/p&gt;

\[u=\ \frac{\partial\psi}{\partial y}\]

\[v=\ -\frac{\partial\psi}{\partial x}\]

\[\psi\left(y,x\right)=\ U_\infty l\left(x\right)f(\eta)\]

\[\eta=\frac{y}{l(x)}=\frac{y}{x}\sqrt{\frac{Ux}{v}}=\frac{y}{x}\sqrt{Re}\]

\[l\left(x\right)\cong\ \sqrt{\frac{\nu x}{U_\infty}}\]

&lt;p&gt;Here, l(x) is proportional the height of the boundary layer, making η a normalized value for our position in the boundary layer. In addition, f(η) and η are both dimensionless. We should also be able to see that:&lt;/p&gt;

\[f\left(\eta\right)\cong{\psi\]

\[f}^\prime\left(\eta\right)\cong{u,\ v\]

\[f}^{\prime\prime}\left(\eta\right)\cong\tau\]

&lt;p&gt;Re-writing the Prandtl boundary layer equations in terms of our similarity variables, we find an exact solution:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\dddot{f}\left(\eta\right)+f\left(\eta\right)\ddot{f}\left(\eta\right)=0\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;falkner-skan-2d-solution&quot;&gt;Falkner-Skan 2D Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Falkner-Skan solution describes boundary layer flow over a wedge. It is a generalization of the Blasius flat plate boundary layer. Using the same similarity definition as above, the exact solution takes the following form. As with the Blasius solution, a numerical approach is required to find a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\dddot{f}+f\ddot{f}+\beta(1+{\dot{f}}^2)=0\]

&lt;p&gt;The velocity in the free stream (i.e. ur in the direction of πB) can be represented by the following equation, as a function of the turning angle:&lt;/p&gt;

\[u_e=Kx^m\]

\[\beta=\frac{2m}{1+m}\]

&lt;p&gt;In the limiting case where B = 0, you get the Blasius flat plate general solution. In the limit that B = 1, you get stagnation point flow. There are tabulated values for the velocity thickness, displacement thickness, momentum thickness, and friction coefficient for a range of B values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blasius-solution-a-2d-flat-plate-1st-order-solution&quot;&gt;Blasius Solution a 2D Flat Plate (1st Order Solution)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Blasius solution is an exact differential solution of the boundary layer equations for flow over a flat plate, however, solving it requires a numerical approach.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{\delta}{x}=\frac{5}{\sqrt{Re}}\]

\[\frac{\delta^\ast}{x}=\frac{1.72}{\sqrt{Re}}\]

\[\frac{\theta}{x}=\frac{0.664}{\sqrt{Re}}\]

\[c_f=\frac{0.664}{\sqrt{Re}}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approximate-solutions-to-2d-boundary-layer&quot;&gt;Approximate Solutions to 2D Boundary Layer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thwaites method uses the Von-Karman integral equations to approximate the boundary layer characteristics. The Von Karman integral relation (steady flow with impermeable wall):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{c_f}{2}=\frac{d\theta}{dx}+(2+H)\frac{\theta}{U}\frac{dU}{dx}\]

&lt;p&gt;This equation is still an exact relationship. Thwaites method is to make the following approximation: (where P(x) is any generic function of x, and is there to characterize the changes in the velocity profile shape in the boundary layer as a function of the x position)&lt;/p&gt;

\[u(x,y)\approx U\left(x\right)f(\eta,P\left(x\right))\]

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Thwaites method, the following parameter is defined:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\lambda=\left(\frac{\theta}{\delta}\right)^2\frac{\delta^2}{v}\frac{dU_e}{dx}=\frac{\theta^2}{v}\frac{dU_e}{dx}\]

&lt;p&gt;The Von-Karman integral relation can then be re-written, and we see that the terms of the original expression are going to be proportional to the parameter defined above.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{\tau_w\theta}{\mu U}=\frac{U\theta}{v}\frac{d\theta}{dx}+(2+H)\frac{\theta^2U^\prime}{v}\]

\[\frac{\tau_w\theta}{\mu U}\approx Shear\ Factor\ Correlation=S(\lambda)\]

\[H=\ \frac{\delta^\ast}{\theta}\approx Shape\ Factor\ Correlation=H(\lambda)\]

&lt;p&gt;For an external flow problem, the following expression for momentum thickness can be derived:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\theta^2=\frac{0.45v}{U_e^6(x)}\int_{0}^{x}{U_e^5(x\prime)}dx\prime\]

&lt;p&gt;The displacement thickness can be solved by using the following shape factor correlation, as a function of λ.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\delta^\ast=\theta H\left(\lambda\right)\]

\[H\left(\lambda\right)=2+4.14z-83.5z^2+854z^3-3337z^4+4576z^5\]

\[z=0.25-\lambda\]

&lt;p&gt;The laminar boundary layer separates when λ = -0.09.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pressure-gradient-effects&quot;&gt;Pressure Gradient Effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three regimes for the pressure gradient term: favorable (less than zero), adverse (greater than zero), and neutral (equal to zero).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An adverse pressure gradient can cause boundary layer separation. Separation occurs at the point where the wall shear stress is equal to zero (slope of the velocity profile is zero), that is:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\tau_w=\mu\frac{du}{dy}=0\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;axis-symmetric-3d-boundary-layers&quot;&gt;Axis-Symmetric 3D Boundary Layers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boundary layer equations for an axisymmetric steady flow without swirl can be shown to be equal to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Axisymmetric steady flow without swirl:&lt;/strong&gt; in other words, flow only occurs in the radial or axial direction, and never in azimuth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

\[\frac{\partial(r_ou)}{\partial x}+r_o\frac{\partial v}{\partial y}=0\]

\[\rho\left(u\frac{\partial u}{\partial x}+v\frac{\partial u}{\partial y}\right)=\rho u_e\frac{\partial u_e}{\partialx}+\mu\frac{\partial^2u}{\partial y^2}\]

&lt;p&gt;The above equations can be transformed into an equivalent set of 2D boundary layer equations with the Mangler Transformation of the coordinate frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fanno-flow&quot;&gt;Fanno Flow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Associated with one dimensional flow with friction. Friction tends to drive flow eventually towards sonic conditions, regardless of whether flow starts out subsonic or supersonic. Given conditions at a point (1) in a pipe, you can solve for the sonic conditions (*). If you then know something about conditions at another point (2), you can use the sonic conditions to backtrack and find all other properties at that second point. In a Fanno flow table, you will usually find the following relations:&lt;/p&gt;

\[M_1\ \ \ \ \ \frac{fL}{D}\ \ \ \ \ \frac{P}{P^\ast}\ \ \ \ \ \ \frac{T}{T^\ast}\ \ \ \ \ \ \frac{P_0}{P_0^\ast}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rayleigh-flow&quot;&gt;Rayleigh Flow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Fanno flow, where heat addition tends to drive flow towards sonic conditions, regardless of initial velocity. Knowing heat input can allow you to find change in total temperature between two points. From there you can backtrack and solve for all other properties at those two points like how you would do it for Fanno flow.&lt;/p&gt;

\[T_{t,2}=\frac{q}{c_p}+T_{t,1}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;laminar-free-stream-shear-flow-jets-wakes-mixing-layers&quot;&gt;Laminar Free Stream Shear Flow (Jets, Wakes, Mixing Layers)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A class of problems involving a large unbounded region and either excess momentum (i.e. a jet or plume) or a momentum deficit (i.e. wake). This section will be completed at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Compressible Flow</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//compressible/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//compressible</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While viscous flow deals with liquids, or flows that are very slow, compressible flow is for your rockets and airplanes. In this Reynold’s number regime, the density of a fluid cannot assumed to be constant, but luckily we can ignore viscous effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#stagnation-properties&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-stagnation-properties&quot;&gt;Stagnation Properties&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#waves&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-waves&quot;&gt;Waves&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#acoustic-wave-theory&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-acoustic-wave-theory&quot;&gt;Acoustic Wave Theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#method-of-characteristics&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-method-of-characteristics&quot;&gt;Method of Characteristics&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1d-unsteady-moc&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-1d-unsteady-moc&quot;&gt;1D Unsteady MOC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2d-steady-moc&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-2d-steady-moc&quot;&gt;2D Steady MOC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#minimum-length-nozzle-calculation-using-moc&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-minimum-length-nozzle-calculation-using-moc&quot;&gt;Minimum Length Nozzle Calculation using MOC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#shocks&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-shocks&quot;&gt;Shocks&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#normal-shocks&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-normal-shocks&quot;&gt;Normal Shocks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#oblique-shocks&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-oblique-shocks&quot;&gt;Oblique Shocks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#detached-shock&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-detached-shock&quot;&gt;Detached Shock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#expansion-fans&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-expansion-fans&quot;&gt;Expansion Fans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#prandtl-meyer-function&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-prandtl-meyer-function&quot;&gt;Prandtl-Meyer Function&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#reflections&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-reflections&quot;&gt;Reflections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#interactions-of-shockwaves&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-interactions-of-shockwaves&quot;&gt;Interactions of Shockwaves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#expansion-wave-interactions-method-of-characteristics&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-expansion-wave-interactions-method-of-characteristics&quot;&gt;Expansion Wave Interactions (Method of Characteristics)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#compressible-boundary-layers&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-compressible-boundary-layers&quot;&gt;Compressible Boundary Layers&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#adiabatic-wall-temperature&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-adiabatic-wall-temperature&quot;&gt;Adiabatic Wall Temperature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stagnation-properties&quot;&gt;Stagnation Properties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any steady state fluid in motion, we can define stagnation/total properties. These reflect the actual values if the fluid were brought to rest isentropically.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{T_{Total}}{T}=\ \left(\frac{P_{Total}}{P}\right)^\sfrac{\gamma-1}{\gamma}=\left(\frac{\rho_{Total}}{\rho}\right)^{\gamma-1}=1+\left(\frac{\gamma-1}{2}\right)M^2\]

&lt;p&gt;Note that the stagnation properties are frame dependent and thus not intrinsic thermodynamic properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;waves&quot;&gt;Waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of fluid dynamics, a wave is simply a disturbance which propagates. This disturbance can have many properties and effects on the fluid as it passes through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It can increase/decrease a property of the fluid (density, pressure, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It can change the velocity of the fluid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The magnitude of the change can be large or small&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The shape of the disturbance can be continuous or discontinuous&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It can be isentropic/increase entropy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It can propagate faster than the local acoustic speed or at the acoustic speed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this definition, a shock is a type of wave. Although shocks are often introduced as “stationary” objects, this is because we have shifted our frame of reference such that this the case. A shock can be stationary (like at the inlet of a ramjet), or a shock can propagate (like out from an explosion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
Another way to think of waves is as the propagation of information. Here&apos;s an example you might be familiar with: take a water droplet hitting the surface of a pond. Waves carry information about the event (the falling water) outwards. The speed at which the wave moves out is the speed at which this information is carried. 

Every fluid has a local &quot;acoustic speed&quot; or **speed of sound**. This is the maximum speed at which waves can propagate. So here&apos;s a question for you, what happens when a disturbing even (like an airplane) moves faster than the local speed of sound? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acoustic-wave-theory&quot;&gt;Acoustic Wave Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An acoustic wave is the propagation of wave with small magnitude through a medium. This wave travels at the local acoustic speed of the medium and is adiabatic (i.e. the energy of the medium before and after the wave has passed through remains constant). 
Given the initial conditions about the displacement and rate, the solution for the propagation of that disturbance can be found (d’Alembert’s Formula).&lt;/p&gt;

\[∆px,t=0=fx\]

\[∂∆p∂tx,t=0=gx\]

\[∆px,t=fx-a∞t+fx+a∞t2+12a∞x-a∞tx+a∞tgsds\]

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental result is that the initial disturbance splits into a left running and right running portion. The fluid velocity, pressure and density can also be related to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

\[∆u= ±a∞ρ∞∆ρ\]

\[∆ρ= ±1a∞2∆P\]

\[∆ρ= ±1ρ∞a∞∆P\]

&lt;p&gt;In deriving the above equation, we’ve assumed small amplitudes, meaning that the local speed of sound remains constant through the disturbance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we remove this assumption, the local speed at which the disturbance propagates will be proportional to the magnitude and shape of the disturbance. This leads to finite strength waves and the method of characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-of-characteristics&quot;&gt;Method of Characteristics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright here’s where it get complicated. It turns out that when we no longer assume a constant speed of sound, the equations are a tad unsolvable as they are. To this end, mathemeticians have defined a way around this. Instead of solving the entire system for every point in space, we can define some &lt;em&gt;characteristic lines&lt;/em&gt;. We can apply a constraint (i.e. some property is constant along the line), and this gives us the final equation we need to solve the system. Then if we define many lines, we can nearly cover the entire region we are solving for. By applying constraints at their intersection points, we can solve a big system of equations and have an approximate solution to our problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1d-unsteady-moc&quot;&gt;1D Unsteady MOC&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, well I’ve outlined the principle behind it, but I need to actually write the section on how to do this. :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2d-steady-moc&quot;&gt;2D Steady MOC&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;minimum-length-nozzle-calculation-using-moc&quot;&gt;Minimum Length Nozzle Calculation using MOC&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With MOC, it is possible to design a nozzle such that the local curvature exactly cancels any incident expansion waves (these result from the diverging section right after the throat). 
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;shocks&quot;&gt;Shocks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shocks occur when objects travel faster than the acoustic speed of the fluid it’s in (speed measured relative to the fluid). This leads to a sudden discontinuity in the fluid’s properties as it transitions from supersonic to subsonic velocities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;normal-shocks&quot;&gt;Normal Shocks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across a normal shock: total temperature remains constant, total pressure decreases, but static pressure and static temperature increase. Density increases, speed decreases. 
Derivation of Normal Shock Equations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continuity Equation: 				\(\rho_1u_1=\rho_2u_2\)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Momentum Conservation Equation:		\({P_1+\rho}_1{u_1}^2=P_2+\rho_2{u_2}^2\)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy Conservation Equation		\(h_1+\frac{1}{2}u_1^2=h_2+\frac{1}{2}u_2^2\)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ideal Gas Law					\(PV=nRT\)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calorically Perfect Gas Assumption		\(h=\ C_pT\)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above represents 5 equations with 5 unknowns (assuming we know the properties at state 1, upstream of the shock). They can be solved to show the following equations:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{P_2}{P_1}=1+\frac{2\gamma}{\gamma+1}\left(M_1^2-1\right)\]

\[\frac{T_2}{T_1}=\left[1+\frac{2\gamma}{\gamma+1}\left(M_1^2-1\right)\right]\left[\frac{2+(\gamma-1)M_1^2}{(\gamma+1)M_1^2}\right]\]

\[\frac{\rho_2}{\rho_1}=\frac{u_1}{u_2}=\frac{(\gamma+1)M_1^2}{2+(\gamma-1)M_1^2}\]

\[{M_2}^2=\frac{1+\frac{\gamma-1}{2}M_1^2}{\gamma M_1^2-\frac{\gamma-1}{2}}\]

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;oblique-shocks&quot;&gt;Oblique Shocks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supersonic flow over an angle. From the conservation equations, there are two equally valid solutions to an oblique shock problem, a strong solution and a weak solution. It is also possible that for a given combination of turning angle and incoming Mach number, there is no solution. Instead, the oblique shock becomes a detached or bow shock.&lt;/p&gt;

\[M_{n,1}=M_1\sin{\left(\sigma\right)}\]

\[M_2=\ \frac{M_{2n}}{\sin\funcapply(\sigma-\delta)}\]

\[\tan{\left(\delta\right)}=2\cot\funcapply(\sigma)\left[\frac{M_1^2{sin}^2\left(\sigma\right)-1}{M_1^2\left(\gamma+cos\left(2\sigma\right)\right)+2}\right]\]

&lt;p&gt;Unless there is some downstream flow feature to support the strong shock, the weak solution is typically what develops. 
The presence of a shock introduces a sudden change in the fluid properties, including pressure. This leads to the creation of wave drag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some important takeaways from the above figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The red line denotes the maximum shock wave angle that is possible for a given incoming Mach number and deflection angle. If either one is increased while the other is kept constant, the shock will detach.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After a strong shock, the fluid is always subsonic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fter a weak shock, the fluid can be either subsonic OR supersonic. This is the region bounded by the red and blue dotted lines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The strong limit is the normal shock.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;detached-shock&quot;&gt;Detached Shock&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The detached or bow shock is just an oblique shock problem in which a range of deflection angles (0 to 90 degrees) are present. At the centerline, fluid flow is perfectly perpendicular to the bow shock, and so it is treated as a normal shock. Traveling away from the center, the fluid flow has velocity partially parallel to the shock. This is equivalent to an oblique shock at some deflection angle. Infinitely far away, the deflection angle reaches 0 degrees and hence no shock develops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that there are two regions behind the bow shock, a subsonic flow region, and a supersonic flow region. The dividing line between these two regimes is defined by the point along the bow shock where M2 = 1, or the blue dotted line in the figure above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;expansion-fans&quot;&gt;Expansion Fans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact opposite of an oblique shock, in which the boundary curves away from the flow direction. An expansion fan is formed as a continuous spread of Mach/Acoustic waves, each providing some infinitesimal change to the fluid properties. Thus, flow through an expansion fan is isentropic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prandtl-meyer-function&quot;&gt;Prandtl-Meyer Function&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flow angle can be related to the local Mach number by applying continuity and conservation laws across an expansion wave. The resulting expression is the Prandtl-Meyer Function.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\theta_2-\theta_1=v\left(M_2\right)-v(M_1)\]

\[v\left(M\right)=\ \sqrt{\frac{\gamma+1}{\gamma-1}}arctan\sqrt{\frac{\gamma-1}{\gamma+1}(M^2-1)}-arctan\sqrt{M^2-1}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reflections&quot;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a solid boundary, waves reflect in a like manner. That is, a shock reflects as a shock, and an expansion wave reflects as an expansion wave. This maintains the kinematic constraint that flow near a wall must be parallel to it (i.e. no penetration).
At a free boundary, waves reflect in opposite manners. A shock reflects as an expansion wave, while an expansion wave reflects and converges as a shock. Across a free boundary, the pressure must be equal, and the flow in both regions must be parallel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interactions-of-shockwaves&quot;&gt;Interactions of Shockwaves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TBD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;expansion-wave-interactions-method-of-characteristics&quot;&gt;Expansion Wave Interactions (Method of Characteristics)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TBD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compressible-boundary-layers&quot;&gt;Compressible Boundary Layers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key feature of compressible boundary layers is that temperature and enthalpy changes cannot be decoupled from the velocity profile. Thus, even if the wall is adiabatic, the flow itself is neither adiabatic or isentropic (viscous dissipation). Consider the steady case where Prandtl number is equal to 1 (not a bad assumption with gases). This is also known as the Crocco-Busemann Relations.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\Pr{=\ \frac{\mu C_p}{k}}\]

&lt;p&gt;For an arbitrary pressure gradient, the temperature distribution takes the following form. This condition is satisfied for isentropic flow outside the boundary layer.&lt;/p&gt;

\[T=T_e\left[1+\frac{\gamma-1}{2}M_e^2\left(1-\frac{u^2}{U_e^2}\right)\right]\]

&lt;p&gt;For this scenario, the adiabatic wall temperature is equal to the stagnation temperature of the free stream. Recovery factor is 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second scenario is for zero pressure gradient.&lt;/p&gt;

\[T-T_w=\left(T_{oe}-T_w\right)\frac{u}{U_e}-\frac{u^2}{2C_p}\]

&lt;p&gt;The similar solution to the adiabatic wall temperature can be found for cases of Prandtl number larger than one with the following expression.&lt;/p&gt;

\[T_{aw}=T_e\left[1+\frac{\gamma-1}{2}\sqrt{Pr}M_e^2\right]\]

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adiabatic-wall-temperature&quot;&gt;Adiabatic Wall Temperature&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the wall temperature for a fluid flow such that there is no net heat transfer into or out of the wall. If a system is let to run until equilibrium, this is the steady state temperature the immersed object will reach.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Turbulent Flow</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//turbulent/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//turbulent</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In general, turbulent flow is modeled statistically. Averages values are used instead of exact ones. Before laminar flow becomes fully turbulent, it experiences transition. Transition begins with flow instability. The point at which a flow trips into instability (critical point) is distinct from the point at which flow transitions fully to turbulence (transition point).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;squires-law&quot;&gt;Squire’s Law&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For two-dimensional parallel flow, the minimum critical unstable Reynold’s number occurs for a two-dimensional disturbance propagating in the same direction. Really all that this Law states is that a turbulence is tripped in the direction of disturbances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;orr-sommerfeld-equation&quot;&gt;Orr-Sommerfeld Equation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equation describing the velocity distribution of a two-dimensional disturbance propagating in the same direction as a two-dimensional parallel flow can found to be exactly:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\left(U-c\right)\left(\phi^{\prime\prime}-\alpha^2\phi\right)-U^{\prime\prime}\phi+i\frac{\mathbit{\nu}}{\alpha}\left(\phi^{\prime\prime\prime\prime}-2\alpha^2\phi^{\prime\prime}+\alpha^4\phi\right)=\ 0\]

\[\Psi\left(x,y,t\right)=\ \phi\left(y\right)exp\left(i\left[\alpha x-\beta t\right]\right)\]

\[c=\sfrac{\beta}{\alpha}\]

&lt;p&gt;Where U is the velocity of the free stream, α is the wavenumber, c is the wave speed, and the frequency, ω = αc. The primes denote differentiation with respect to y. This is a fourth order linear differential equation. Disturbances must vanish at walls and an infinity. The temporal growth and spatial growth of disturbances are functions of the following form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Temporal: \(f\left(Re,\ \alpha,\ c_r,\ c_i\right)=0\)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spatial: \(g\left(Re,\ \alpha_r,\ \alpha_i,\ \omega\right)=0\)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temporal neutral stability occurs when ci is equal to zero, while spatial neutral stability occurs for αi equal to zero. Instability begins at ci greater than zero. A full analytical solution of the Orr-Sommerfeld equation is non-trivial. In general, a non-dimensionalized version of the Orr-Sommerfeld equation can be written and can be plotted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wavenumber&quot;&gt;Wavenumber&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wavenumber is the waves per unit space. It is distinct from frequency, which is the waves per unit time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rayleigh-inviscid-stability-theory&quot;&gt;Rayleigh Inviscid Stability Theory&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the limiting case where the viscous term in the Orr-Sommerfeld equation is neglected. In particular, the following five theorems are outlined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is necessary for instability that the velocity profile have a point of inflection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is further necessary for instability that the numerical value of U’ of the vorticity be a maximum at the point of inflection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a point of inflection exists, it is further necessary that U’’(U-UPI) &amp;lt; 0 somewhere on the profile.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If U(y) possesses an inflection point, a neutral disturbance may exist who phase velocity is given by cr.
  The phase velocity of an amplified disturbance must always lie between the minimum and maximum values of U(y).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;predicting-instability--transition-in-practice&quot;&gt;Predicting Instability &amp;amp; Transition in Practice&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was found that for many different profiles and conditions, the critical transition Reynold’s number seems to depend only on the shape factor. Thus, if the shape factor can be found, one can predict the point of instability and transition. 
Several models have been proposed to find an equivalent transition point. Wazzan uses a similar approach to instability and finds a transition Reynold’s number as a function of the shape factor. There is no universal curve that accounts for free stream turbulence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;improving-stability&quot;&gt;Improving Stability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A favorable pressure gradient (decreasing pressure) delays the onset of instability, or in cases bring a flow back into stability. Boundary layers in gases are stabilized by cooling the wall, while boundary layers in liquids are stabilized by heating the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transition-to-turbulence&quot;&gt;Transition to Turbulence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps leading to fully developed turbulence are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-linear development waves (Tollmien-Schlichting Waves)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Three-dimensional instability and streamwise vortices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Formation of turbulent spots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fully developed turbulence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reynolds-averaged-navier-stokes-equation-rans&quot;&gt;Reynolds-Averaged Navier Stokes Equation (RANS)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are time averaged forms of the Navier-Stokes equations. Properties of the fluid are expressed in terms of an average and fluctuation term. An especially interesting result is the resultant equation for local stress.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\tau=\ \mu\left[\frac{\partial\bar{u}}{\partial\bar{y}}+\frac{\partial\bar{v}}{\partial\bar{x}}\right]-\rho\bar{u\prime v\prime}\]

&lt;p&gt;The first term is the laminar stress, while the second term is an equivalent turbulent “Reynolds Stress”. Importantly, note that it is independent of viscosity. This means that in regions dominated by the Reynold’s stress, viscosity of the fluid is unimportant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wall-bounded-turbulent-flow&quot;&gt;Wall Bounded Turbulent Flow&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the wall, fluctuations must be near zero, so laminar contributions are more important. Away from the wall, turbulent stress dominates. The velocity profile from a wall then has three components, a viscous dominates inner layer, a turbulent dominated outer layer, and an overlap layer. First, we define the friction velocity:&lt;/p&gt;

\[v^\ast=\sqrt{\frac{\tau_w}{\rho}}\]

&lt;p&gt;The average velocity and position are also re-written.&lt;/p&gt;

\[u^+=\frac{\bar{u}}{v^\ast}\]

\[y^+=\frac{\rho v^\ast y}{\mu}\]

&lt;p&gt;The following is equation can then model the inner layer, overlap layer, and outer layer.&lt;/p&gt;

\[u^+=\frac{1}{k}\ln{\left(y^+\right)}+B+\frac{2\Pi}{k}f(\eta)\]

\[f\left(\eta\right)=\sin^2{\left(\frac{\pi}{2}\eta\right)}\]

&lt;p&gt;Where k and B are universal constants equal to 0.41 and 5.0 respectively. The first term captures the logarithmic relationship in the overlap section, while the second capture the diverging effect in the outer layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very, very near the wall, viscous and laminar forces dominate. The velocity profile in this region is linear and proportional to the wall stress. It is called the viscous sublayer.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\tau_w=\mu\frac{\bar{u}}{\bar{y}}\]

\[u^+=y^+\]

&lt;h4 id=&quot;turbulent-pipe-flow&quot;&gt;Turbulent Pipe Flow&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the above model, you can actually derive an expression for the Darcy-friction factor from the flow equation. Note that this is for a smooth pipe, and so when possible, you should still reference a moody chart. In any case, the following is useful for seeing that the Darcy-Friction is not just an empirically derived fit.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{1}{\Lambda^{1/2}}=2.0\log_{10}{\left({Re}_D\Lambda^\frac{1}{2}\right)}-0.8\]

\[Notably the following trends come out:\]

\[\tau\approx0.0396\rho^{3/4}\mu^{7/4}D^{-1/4}{U_{avg}}^{7/4}\]

&lt;h4 id=&quot;turbulent-boundary-layers&quot;&gt;Turbulent Boundary Layers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the wall bounded turbulent model, the skin coefficient term can be approximated in terms of the boundary layer thickness Reynolds number. Meanwhile, the momentum thickness is evaluated by using a one-seventh power law profile taken from pipe flow data.&lt;/p&gt;

\[C_f=2\frac{d\theta}{dx}\]

\[\frac{\bar{u}}{U_e}\approx\left(\frac{y}{\delta}\right)^{1/7}\]

\[C_f\approx0.020{Re}_\delta^{-1/6}\]

\[{Re}_\delta\approx0.16{Re}_x^{6/7}\]

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Miscellaneous Topics</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//misc/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//reference</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a series of random topics, including non-dimensional numbers and fluid statics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-dimensional-numbers&quot;&gt;Non-Dimensional Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a whole bunch. Here are the main ones that you might come across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reynolds-number&quot;&gt;Reynold’s Number&lt;/h4&gt;

\[\frac{\rho UL}{\mu}\]

&lt;p&gt;Ratio of viscous forces to inertia forces. Determines flow regime (Laminar, turbulent, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mach-number&quot;&gt;Mach Number&lt;/h4&gt;

\[\frac{u}{a}\]

&lt;p&gt;Ratio of flow velocity to speed of sound. The higher the Mach number, the more irreversible the flow becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;knudsen-number&quot;&gt;Knudsen Number&lt;/h4&gt;

\[\frac{\lambda}{L}\]

&lt;p&gt;Ratio of molecular mean free path to characteristic length. Determines transition from gas dynamics to continuum mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prandtl-number&quot;&gt;Prandtl Number&lt;/h4&gt;

\[\frac{C_p\mu}{k}\]

&lt;p&gt;Ratio of momentum diffusivity to thermal diffusivity. In other words, ratio of the dominance of convection to conduction. Also relates momentum vs thermal boundary layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stokes-number&quot;&gt;Stokes Number&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nusselt-number&quot;&gt;Nusselt Number&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fluid-statics&quot;&gt;Fluid Statics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forces always act perpendicular to the surface. Given atmospheric surface pressure (free surface) the pressure at a depth (h) will be:&lt;/p&gt;

\[P=\ \gamma h\]

&lt;p&gt;Where \(\gamma\) is the specific gravity of the liquid, (1 for water). For submerged plate of area, A, total resultant force is equal to:&lt;/p&gt;

\[F_r=\gamma h_cA\]

&lt;p&gt;Where hc is the depth of the centroid of the plate. This total force DOES NOT act through the centroid however, instead it acts at through a point where the total moment is equal to zero (center of pressure or can think of this as the centroid of the pressure distribution). If the plate is symmetric, this will coincide with the centroid. 
For curved surfaces, use the following force balance approach:&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introducing Hyde</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//2013/12/28/introducing-hyde/"/>
   <updated>2013-12-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//2013/12/28/introducing-hyde</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hyde is a brazen two-column &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; theme that pairs a prominent sidebar with uncomplicated content. It’s based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://getpoole.com&quot;&gt;Poole&lt;/a&gt;, the Jekyll butler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;built-on-poole&quot;&gt;Built on Poole&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poole is the Jekyll Butler, serving as an upstanding and effective foundation for Jekyll themes by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mdo&quot;&gt;@mdo&lt;/a&gt;. Poole, and every theme built on it (like Hyde here) includes the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complete Jekyll setup included (layouts, config, &lt;a href=&quot;/404&quot;&gt;404&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/atom.xml&quot;&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;, posts, and &lt;a href=&quot;/about&quot;&gt;example page&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly design and development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easily scalable text and component sizing with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rem&lt;/code&gt; units in the CSS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for a wide gamut of HTML elements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Related posts (time-based, because Jekyll) below each post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Syntax highlighting, courtesy Pygments (the Python-based code snippet highlighter)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hyde-features&quot;&gt;Hyde features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the features of Poole, Hyde adds the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sidebar includes support for textual modules and a dynamically generated navigation with active link support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two orientations for content and sidebar, default (left sidebar) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/lanyon#reverse-layout&quot;&gt;reverse&lt;/a&gt; (right sidebar), available via &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; classes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/hyde#themes&quot;&gt;Eight optional color schemes&lt;/a&gt;, available via &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/hyde#readme&quot;&gt;Head to the readme&lt;/a&gt; to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;browser-support&quot;&gt;Browser support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hyde is by preference a forward-thinking project. In addition to the latest versions of Chrome, Safari (mobile and desktop), and Firefox, it is only compatible with Internet Explorer 9 and above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;download&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hyde is developed on and hosted with GitHub. Head to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/hyde&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt; for downloads, bug reports, and features requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Example content</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//2012/02/07/example-content/"/>
   <updated>2012-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//2012/02/07/example-content</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
  Howdy! This is an example blog post that shows several types of HTML content supported in this theme.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;dis parturient montes&lt;/a&gt;, nascetur ridiculus mus. &lt;em&gt;Aenean eu leo quam.&lt;/em&gt; Pellentesque ornare sem lacinia quam venenatis vestibulum. Sed posuere consectetur est at lobortis. Cras mattis consectetur purus sit amet fermentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Curabitur blandit tempus porttitor. Nullam quis risus eget urna mollis ornare vel eu leo. Nullam id dolor id nibh ultricies vehicula ut id elit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Etiam porta &lt;strong&gt;sem malesuada magna&lt;/strong&gt; mollis euismod. Cras mattis consectetur purus sit amet fermentum. Aenean lacinia bibendum nulla sed consectetur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inline-html-elements&quot;&gt;Inline HTML elements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTML defines a long list of available inline tags, a complete list of which can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element&quot;&gt;Mozilla Developer Network&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To bold text&lt;/strong&gt;, use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;To italicize text&lt;/em&gt;, use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abbreviations, like &lt;abbr title=&quot;HyperText Markup Langage&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; should use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;abbr&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, with an optional &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;title&lt;/code&gt; attribute for the full phrase.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citations, like &lt;cite&gt;— Mark otto&lt;/cite&gt;, should use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;cite&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Deleted&lt;/del&gt; text should use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;del&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;ins&gt;inserted&lt;/ins&gt; text should use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;ins&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Superscript &lt;sup&gt;text&lt;/sup&gt; uses &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and subscript &lt;sub&gt;text&lt;/sub&gt; uses &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these elements are styled by browsers with few modifications on our part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;Heading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vivamus sagittis lacus vel augue rutrum faucibus dolor auctor. Duis mollis, est non commodo luctus, nisi erat porttitor ligula, eget lacinia odio sem nec elit. Morbi leo risus, porta ac consectetur ac, vestibulum at eros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;code&quot;&gt;Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;code element&lt;/code&gt; montes, nascetur ridiculus mus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot; data-lang=&quot;js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Example can be run directly in your JavaScript console
&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Create a function that takes two arguments and returns the sum of those arguments
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;adder&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;return a + b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Call the function
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;adder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// &amp;gt; 8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aenean lacinia bibendum nulla sed consectetur. Etiam porta sem malesuada magna mollis euismod. Fusce dapibus, tellus ac cursus commodo, tortor mauris condimentum nibh, ut fermentum massa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gists-via-github-pages&quot;&gt;Gists via GitHub Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vestibulum id ligula porta felis euismod semper. Nullam quis risus eget urna mollis ornare vel eu leo. Donec sed odio dui.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;400: Invalid request&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/5555251.js?file=gist.md&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aenean eu leo quam. Pellentesque ornare sem lacinia quam venenatis vestibulum. Nullam quis risus eget urna mollis ornare vel eu leo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Donec sed odio dui. Vestibulum id ligula porta felis euismod semper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lists&quot;&gt;Lists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Aenean lacinia bibendum nulla sed consectetur. Etiam porta sem malesuada magna mollis euismod. Fusce dapibus, tellus ac cursus commodo, tortor mauris condimentum nibh, ut fermentum massa justo sit amet risus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Praesent commodo cursus magna, vel scelerisque nisl consectetur et.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donec id elit non mi porta gravida at eget metus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nulla vitae elit libero, a pharetra augue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donec ullamcorper nulla non metus auctor fringilla. Nulla vitae elit libero, a pharetra augue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vestibulum id ligula porta felis euismod semper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maecenas sed diam eget risus varius blandit sit amet non magna.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cras mattis consectetur purus sit amet fermentum. Sed posuere consectetur est at lobortis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;HyperText Markup Language (HTML)&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;The language used to describe and define the content of a Web page&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;Cascading Style Sheets (CSS)&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Used to describe the appearance of Web content&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;JavaScript (JS)&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;The programming language used to build advanced Web sites and applications&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integer posuere erat a ante venenatis dapibus posuere velit aliquet. Morbi leo risus, porta ac consectetur ac, vestibulum at eros. Nullam quis risus eget urna mollis ornare vel eu leo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;images&quot;&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quisque consequat sapien eget quam rhoncus, sit amet laoreet diam tempus. Aliquam aliquam metus erat, a pulvinar turpis suscipit at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://placehold.it/800x400&quot; alt=&quot;placeholder&quot; title=&quot;Large example image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://placehold.it/400x200&quot; alt=&quot;placeholder&quot; title=&quot;Medium example image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://placehold.it/200x200&quot; alt=&quot;placeholder&quot; title=&quot;Small example image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tables&quot;&gt;Tables&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aenean lacinia bibendum nulla sed consectetur. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Upvotes&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Downvotes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tfoot&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Totals&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tfoot&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bob&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Charlie&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nullam id dolor id nibh ultricies vehicula ut id elit. Sed posuere consectetur est at lobortis. Nullam quis risus eget urna mollis ornare vel eu leo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to see something else added? &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/poole/issues/new&quot;&gt;Open an issue.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What's Jekyll?</title>
   <link href="https://ludavid15.github.io//whatsJekyll/"/>
   <updated>2012-02-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>https://ludavid15.github.io//whats-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is a static site generator, an open-source tool for creating simple yet powerful websites of all shapes and sizes. From &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/blob/master/README.markdown&quot;&gt;the project’s readme&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a simple, blog aware, static site generator. It takes a template directory […] and spits out a complete, static website suitable for serving with Apache or your favorite web server. This is also the engine behind GitHub Pages, which you can use to host your project’s page or blog right here from GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an immensely useful tool and one we encourage you to use here with Hyde.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll&quot;&gt;visiting the project on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
